Last update: 21-Feb-17

ENAMUL HOQUE PRINCE

University of British Columbia, 201-2366 Main Mall Vancouver, B.C. Canada V6T 1Z4 +1 778 798 0892 enamul@cs.ubc.ca www.cs.ubc.ca/~enamul/

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research focuses on combining information visualization and human-computer interaction with natural language processing to address the challenges of the information overload problem. In particular, I design and develop both text analysis and interactive visualization techniques to explore a large amount of data.

EDUCATION

09/2012-04/2017 University of British Columbia (UBC), Canada

PhD Candidate in Computer Science

Advisor: Dr. Giuseppe Carenini

Committee members: Dr. Tamara Munzner and Dr. Raymond T. Ng Thesis: Visual Text Analytics for Asynchronous Online Conversations

01/2010-01/2012 Memorial University of Newfoundland (MUN), Canada

MSc in Computer Science

Advisors: Dr. Orland Hoeber and Dr. Minglun Gong

Thesis: Concept-based query expansion and interactive visualization for Web

image search

03/2003-08/2007 Chittagong University of Engineering & Technology (CUET), Bangladesh

BSc in Computer Science & Engineering

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

05/2016-08/2016 Tableau Software, Palo Alto, CA, USA

Research Intern.

Developed a natural language interface for exploring visualizations

01/2016- 05/2016 Qatar Computing Research Institute (QCRI), Qatar

Research Associate

Developed and deployed an intelligent visual interface for supporting the exploration of community question answering forums [C9, D1]; developed

and evaluated a speech act classifier [C7] in collaboration.

09/2012-01/2016 University of British Columbia, Canada

Research Assistant

Worked on PhD dissertation [J6, J7, C5, C6, W4]

09/2012-04/2013, University of British Columbia, Canada

09/2016-present Research Assistant

Developed InfoVis systems and ran user studies in the Advanced Tools for

User-Adaptive Visualization (ATUAV) project [J5, C4, W2, W3]

01/2010-12/2011 Memorial University of Newfoundland, Canada

Research Assistant

Worked on MSc thesis [J3, J4, C3, W1]

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, University of British Columbia

Fall 2016, Fall 2015 CPSC 422: Artificial Intelligence 2

Summer 2015 CPSC 213: Introduction to Computer Systems

Winter 2010, Fall Teaching Assistant, Memorial University of Newfoundland

2010, Winter 2011 CS 1700: Computer Basics

03/2008-12/2009 Lecturer, Chittagong University of Engineering and Technology

2009 Object Oriented Programming

2008 Computer Basics and Programming

2008 Algorithm Design

2008 Computer Graphics

2008 Fuzzy Logic & Neural Network

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

JOURNAL PAPERS

[J7] E. Hoque and G. Carenini, Interactive topic modeling for exploring asynchronous online conversations: design and evaluation of ConVisIT, *ACM Transactions on Interactive Intelligent Systems (TIIS)*, Vol. 6, No 1, pp. 7:1-7:24, 2016.

[J6] E. Hoque and G. Carenini, ConVis: A visual text analytic system for exploring blog conversations, *Journal of Computer Graphics Forum (Proc. EuroVis)*, Vol. 33, No. 3, pp. 221-230, 2014, (AR: 22.9%).

[J5] C. Conati, G. Carenini, **E. Hoque**, B. Steichen, D. Toker, Evaluating the impact of user characteristics and different layouts on an interactive visualization for decision making. *Journal of Computer Graphics Forum (Proc. EuroVis)*, Vol. 33, No. 3, pp. 371-380, 2014, (AR: 22.9%).

[J4] E. Hoque, O. Hoeber, M. Gong, CIDER: Concept-based image diversification, exploration, and retrieval, *Journal of Information Processing & Management (IPM)*, Vol. 49, No 5, pp. 1122-1138, 2013.

[J3] E. Hoque, O. Hoeber, M. Gong, Balancing the trade-offs between diversity and precision for Web image search using concept-based query expansion, *Journal of Emerging Technologies in Web Intelligence (JETWI)*, Vol. 4, No 1, pp. 26-34, 2012.

[J2] E. Hoque, O. Hoeber, G. Strong, M. Gong, Combining conceptual query expansion and visual search results exploration for Web image retrieval,

Journal of Ambient Intelligence and Humanized Computing (JAIHC), Vol. 4, No. 3 pp. 389-400, 2011.

[J1] G. Hossain, E. Hoque, M. I. Monir, M. A. Sharif, Automatic stemming and its impact in Bangla information retrieval, Computer Science and Engineering Research Journal (CSERJ), Vol. 5, pp. 17-23, ISSN: 1990-4010, 2008.

- CONFERENCE [C9] E. Hoque S. Joty, L. Màrquez, and G. Carenini, CQAVis: Visual Text PAPERS Analytics for Community Question Answering, In Proceedings of ACM Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI), 2017 (accepted).
 - [C8] S. Joty and E. Hoque, Speech Act Modeling of Written Asynchronous Conversations with Task-Specific Embeddings and Conditional Structured Models, Proceedings of the 54th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), pp. 1746–1756, 2016.
 - [C7] E. Hoque and G. Carenini, MultiConVis: A Visual Text Analytics System for Exploring a Collection of Online Conversations, pp. 96-107 In *Proceedings* of ACM Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI), 2016 (AR: 25.89%).
 - [C6] E Hoque, S. Joty, L. Màrquez, A. Barrón-Cedeño, G. Martino, A. Moschitti, P. Nakov, S. Romeo, and G. Carenini, An Interactive System for Exploring Community Question Answering Forums, International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING), 2016.
 - [C5] E. Hoque and G. Carenini, ConVisIT: Interactive Topic Modeling for Exploring Asynchronous Online Conversations, In *Proceedings of ACM Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI)*, pp. 169-180 2015, (AR: 22.9%).
 - [C4] G. Carenini, C. Conati, E. Hoque, B. Steichen, D. Toker, J. Enns, Highlighting interventions and user differences: informing adaptive information visualization support, In Proceedings of The ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), pp. 1835-1844, 2014 (AR: 23%).
 - [C3] E. Hoque, G. Strong, O. Hoeber, M. Gong, Conceptual query expansion and visual search results exploration for Web image retrieval, In Proceedings of the Atlantic Web Intelligence Conference (AWIC), pp. 73-82, 2011.
 - [C2] G. Strong, E. Hoque, M. Gong, and O. Hoeber, Organizing and browsing image search results based on conceptual and visual similarities, In Proceedings of the International Symposium on Visual Computing, pp. 481-490, 2010.
 - [C1] E. Hoque, G. Hossain, A. A. Dewan, P. Debnath, An audible Bangla text entry method in mobile phones with intelligent keypad design, In *Proceedings* of the International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT), pp.279-284, 2009, (AR: 31%).

WORKSHOP PAPERS [W4] E. Hoque, G. Carenini and S. Joty. Interactive Exploration of Asynchronous Conversations: Applying a User-centered Approach to Design a Visual Text Analytic System. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Interactive Language Learning, Visualization, and Interfaces (ILLVI 2014), in conjunction with the ACL-2014, Baltimore, USA.

> [W3] G. Carenini, C. Conati, E. Hoque, B. Steichen, User Task Adaptation in Multimedia Presentations. Proceedings of the Workshop on User-Adaptive *Information Visualization (WUAV 2013)*, in conjunction with the 21st conference on User Modeling, Adaptation and Personalization (UMAP 2013), Rome, Italy, June 2013.

[W2] C. Conati, E. Hoque, D. Toker, B. Steichen, When to Adapt: Detecting User's Confusion During Visualization Processing, Proceedings of the Workshop on User-Adaptive Information Visualization (WUAV 2013), in conjunction with the 21st conference on User Modeling, Adaptation and Personalization (UMAP 2013), Rome, Italy, June 2013.

[W1] E. Hoque, O. Hoeber, M. Gong, Evaluating the trade-offs between diversity and precision for Web image search using concept-based query expansion, Proceedings of the International Workshop on Intelligent Web *Interaction*, in conjunction with the IEEE/WIC/ACM *International* **Conference on Web Intelligence**, pp. 130-133, Lyon, France, 2011.

POSTERS

[P1] E. Hoque, O. Hoeber, M. Gong, concept-based interactive visualization approach to Web image search (refereed poster), In Conference Compendium of the IEEE Information Visualization, Providence, RI, USA, 2011.

STUDENT CONSORTIUM

[S2] E. Hoque, Visual Text Analytics for Online Conversations: Design, Evaluation, and Applications, In Companion Publication of the International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI), pp. 122-125, 2016.

[S1] E. Hoque, Visual Text Analytics for Asynchronous Online Conversations, In Companion Publication of the International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI), pp. 105-108, 2015.

BOOK CHAPTERS

[B1] G. Murray, E. Hoque and G. Carenini, Opinion Summarization and Visualization, in *Sentiment Analysis in Social Networks*, Eds. Pozzi, Fersini, Messina, Liu. Elsevier, 2016

INVITED TALKS

 MultiConVis: A Visual Text Analytics System for Exploring a Collection of Online Conversations, UBC Laboratory for Computational Intelligence (LCI) Forum Talk, Vancouver, BC, January 2017.

- Visual text analytics for online conversations, *Department of Linguistics*, Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, BC, January 2017.
- An overview of text visualization techniques, *UBC School of Library, Archival and Information Studies (iSchool)*, Vancouver, BC, December 2016.
- ConVis: A visual text analytic system for exploring asynchronous online conversations, *The Pacific Northwest Regional NLP Workshop (NW-NLP)*, Microsoft Research, Redmond, April 2014.
- A visual text analytic system for asynchronous conversations, *UBC Laboratory for Computational Intelligence (LCI) Forum Talk*, Vancouver, BC, November 2013.
- Conceptual query expansion and visual search results exploration for Web image retrieval, *Department of Computer Science*, Memorial University of Newfoundland, St. John's, NL, November 2010.

STUDENTS MENTORED

2013 Rastko Djeric, Undergraduate directed study project
2013 Kaya Gajos, Undergraduate directed study project
2009 Kazi Shahadat Hossain, Undergraduate thesis
2009 Sumon Deb, Undergraduate thesis
2009 Priyanka Guha, Undergraduate thesis
2008 Pijush Debnath, Undergraduate thesis [C1]

AWARDS AND HONORS

2012-2016	Faculty of Science Graduate award, University of British Columbia		
2015, 2016	Travel awards, IUI Conference		
2014	Travel awards, ACL Conference		
2012	Dean's Doctoral Award, Memorial University of Newfoundland (declined)		
2012	Visa differential scholarship, University of Calgary (declined)		
2011	Fellow of the School of Graduate Studies, Memorial University		
2010-2011	School of Graduate Studies Award, Memorial University of Newfoundland		
2003-2007	University Merit Scholarship, Bangladesh		
1995-2000	Primary and High School Talent-pool Scholarship, UNICEF and the		
	Government of Bangladesh		

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Program committee	IIII 2015	IIII 2016	IIII 2017
Program committee	101 2015.	. 101 2010.	101 2017

Referee EuroVis 2017, IUI 2015, 2016, 2017, Journal of Computational Intelligence,

Workshop on Human and Technology (WHAT) 2014

Student volunteer IUI 2016, ACL 2014, Canadian AI/GI/CRV 2011

Representative Graduate Student Admission Committee, University of British Columbia, 2016

Vice-President Bangladesh Student Association, Memorial University of Newfoundland, 2011

Volunteer CS open house program, Memorial University of Newfoundland, 2010

Organizing secretary CUET ICT fête, 2010

Coach Programming teams in national programming contests [2008-09]

AFFILIATION

Student member ACM, IEEE

Member Engineers' Institute, Bangladesh

LEGAL STATUS

Permeant resident of Canada

REFERENCES

Giuseppe Carenini

Associate Professor, Computer Science, University of British Columbia carenini@cs.ubc.ca, + 1 (604) 822-5109

Tamara Munzner

Professor, Computer Science, University of British Columbia tmm@cs.ubc.ca, + 1 (604) 827-5200

Vidva Setlur

Senior Research Scientist, Tableau Software, Palo Alto, CA, USA vsetlur@tableau.com, +1(650) 382-6203

Lluís Màrquez

Principal Scientist, Arabic Language Technologies, Qatar Computing Research Institute

lmarquez@qf.org.qa

Minglun Gong

Professor, Computer Science, Memorial University of Newfoundland gong@cs.mun.ca, +1 (709) 864-3589

Orland Hoeber

Associate Professor, Computer Science, University of Regina orland.hoeber@uregina.ca, +1 (306) 585-4598